Hi, welcome back to Lam Rim.
Remember we're going
through these seven steps
to reach that place where
we have this feeling
of jumping between planets,
and helping people on
all of those planets.
This kind of vision of a bodhisattva.
We're on the third of them.
So MAR SHES means you recognize
that all the people around
you have been your mom.
And then DRIN DRAN we finished,
which was remember all the cool things
they did to take care of you.
Basically, that you didn't die
and you got to be an adult
because of their hard work
every single minute of the day,
and also really suffering
from the financial burden
of bringing you up.
Now we reach the third great category
which is called DRIN GZO.
DRIN is short for BKA' DRIN
which means kindness.
GZO BA means to fix it,
which means to pay it back.
So DRIN GZO means if my moms
have been that nice to me,
then what can I do to pay them back?
How can I pay them back?
I like this.
I think it's very appropriate here
if we add a special verse from
the Three Principal Paths.
I've inserted this verse
because I think it's
especially relevant here.
It goes like this.
I just remember this verse a lot.
I think about it a lot.
,SHUGS DRAG CHU BO BZHI
YI RGYUN GYIS KHYER,
,ZLOG DKA' LAS KYI
'CHING BA DAM POS BSDAMS,
,BDAG 'DZIN LCAGS KYI
DRA BA'I SPUBS SU TSUD,
,MA RIG MUN PA'I SMAG CHEN KUN NAS 'THIBS,
,MU MED SRID PAR SKYE ZHING SKYE BA RU,
,SDUG BSNGAL GSUM GYIS
RGYUN CHAD MED PAR MNAR,
,GNAS SKABS 'DI 'DRAR
GYUR PA'I MA RNAMS KYI,
,NGANG TSUL BSAMS NAS SEMS
MCHOG BSKYED BAR MDZOD,
This is in the Three Principal Paths,
Je Tsongkapa's way of
introducing this idea
of paying back your mom's kindness.
I was in Mongolia many years ago.
I guess it was the 90's.
They had just got their independence.
So religion was allowed again
for the first time in about 75 years.
It was an exciting time to be in Mongolia.
So I said I would give a talk
along with a great teacher,
a great lama, named Bakula Rinpoche.
It was at a stadium.
It was at the largest,
the place they could do it in Mongolia,
which is actually where they
hold the national circus
which is the biggest stadium in Mongolia.
We had a lot of people.
I remember I used this verse.
I started out with this verse
and I was looking at a family.
I was talking about how they would feel
if their daughter turned
out to be their mom.
What if your daughter
turned out to have been your mom before?
And I read this verse and
I explained this verse.
I remember.
Afterwards there was a family
came up to me and they said,
"Please take it back."
I said, "What?"
And they said, "Take it back.
"Don't talk about our
daughter with this verse.
"It's too dark.
"We don't want to use this
verse about our daughter."
So it was a very,
I think they were very sensitive
to the real meaning of the verse.
The verse is very dark and very sad.
It's necessary when we think
about paying our mom back
for the kindness she gave to us.
We have to think of our mom in this way.
So let go through the Tibetan
of Tsongkapa's
Three Principal Paths.
SHUGS DRAG CHU BO BZHI YI RGYUN GYIS KHYER
They are swept away by
four fierce river currents,
ZLOG DKA' LAS KYI 'CHING BA DAM POS BSDAMS
chained up tight in past
deeds, hard to undo.
They are swept away by, for example,
the suffering of being born,
SKYE RGA NA 'CHI
of getting old, of
getting sick and of dying.
There are our mom.
Our mom has fallen into this great river.
This very fast river
and she's been swept downstream.
The river is SKYE RGA NA 'CHI.
She has the suffering
of going through birth
and then she has the suffering of aging.
Every moment since the moment she's born,
an unstoppable aging, like
a candle burning down.
Then she's often times sick in this life.
I translated for the Dalai
Lama's doctor for some years,
two of the greatest Tibetans
doctors in the world.
And I was kind of shocked one day he said,
He was given a talk, he said,
"By the way health is not
normal. Health is abnormal.
"Disease is normal."
And I said, "What?"
And he said, "It's normal for
your elements of your body
"to be out of balance."
That's normal state of human being.
Then to be healthy is
like very rare balance
of all the elements in your body.
The human condition, the normal
condition of human being,
is to be sick.
And if you're health for awhile,
that's just really dumb good luck
that you're healthy for awhile.
So SKYE RGA NA 'CHI
and then our mom must die.
So our moms, those beautiful
people who have been our mom,
they are being swept downstream
by these four kinds of suffering.
,SHUGS DRAG CHU BO BZHI
YI RGYUN GYIS KHYER,
,BZLOG DKA' LAS KYI
'CHING BA DAM POS BSDAMS,
And that's okay
if you're being swept
downstream on a river.
Well you could try to swim
And you could try to swim to the shore.
But their hands are chained
and their legs are chained.
Their hands and legs are chained together.
ZLOG DKA' LAS KYI 'CHING BA
The karma chains.
Maybe if they weren't
chained they could swim
and maybe they could
try to get to the shore.
But they are chained.
Their hands are chained.
Their feet are chained
by the past karma.
They don't really have a
choice. They don't have options.
They don't have option
to change the direction
of their life.
The direction of their life
is largely determined
by what they did in their past lives.
So they don't have options
to try to do something
like save themselves.
They are chained up.
Throw your...
Take your mom, throw her off a cliff
into a raging river,
but before your throw her off the cliff,
chain her arms and legs together.
Think of it that way.
BDAG 'DZIN LCAGS KYI
DRA BA'I SBUBS SU TSUD
Then, just before your
throw her off the cliff,
a lock her in an iron box.
Like an iron cage.
So first of all, chain her hands and legs.
And just for good measure
put her into like a... Zoo cage?
A cage for the animals at the zoo.
Put her into a cage like that.
And then throw that into the river.
Cause that's the chance she's
going to have to escape.
Which is zero.
Then, what's the cage? It's BDAG 'DZIN
It's a misunderstanding her world.
For example, misunderstanding
why your husband's yelling
at you, in that moment.
When you don't understand...
When you come into the kitchen
and your husband starts yelling at you
and you don't understand what's going on
and you yell back.
In a way, you are in a iron cage.
You have just put
yourself in an iron cage.
So now think about this mom
who brought you up,
who kept you from being like an animal.
And now, she's thrown
into this terrible river.
Powerful river.
And her hands are chained
and her legs are chained
by the karma she did in the past.
And, on top of that, the chained mom
is shoved into a cage. A small cage.
And then that is thrown into the river.
MU MED SRID PAR SKYE ZHING SKYE BA RU
They are born... You
guys know MU GSUM MU BZHI
Three... What do you
call it? Parameter, no.
Permutation, three or four permutations.
This MU MED means countless permutations.
It's a interested word.
MU MED means countless permutations.
SKYE ZHING SKYE BA RU
She's born in countless forms.
Animals, different kinds of birds,
different kinds of fish,
different kinds of humans.
SDUG BSNGAL GSUM GYIS
RGYUN CHAD MED PAR MNAR
And she is suffering from
the three kinds of suffering.
RGYUN CHAD MED PA
He is returning to the image
of a stream of a river.
And without a break in that flow,
she is suffering from those
three kinds of suffering.
SDUG BSNGAL GYI SDUG BSNGAL
'GYUR BA'I SDUG BSNGAL
and KHYAB PA 'DU BYED KYI SDUG BSNGAL
What's SDUG BSNGAL GYI SDUG BSNGAL?
Suffering of suffering.
What's the classical example?
A backache, or a foot ache.
SDUG BSNGAL GYI SDUG BSNGAL
Then second one 'GYUR BA'I SDUG BSNGAL
Every time you get a nice dinner,
it changes, you get hungry again.
So suffering of change.
And then KHYAB PA 'DU BYED KYI SDUG BSNGAL
KHYAB PA means covers everywhere.
That basically aging.
That we live in a body which is mortal.
So that's,
KHYAB PA 'DU BYED KYI SDUG BSNGAL
also covers the first two.
So it's just our nature to fall apart.
As you get older, you will have the joy
of having your body fall apart.
Then you exercise, exercise,
and then it keeps falling apart.
It's like holding up a
sand castle or something.
GNAS SKABS 'DI 'DRAR
GYUR PA'I MA RNAMS KYI
NGANG TSUL BSAMS NAS SEMS
MCHOG BSKYED PAR MDZOD
Think about, try to imagine
that all the people around
you have been your mom.
Try to imagine that they have been thrown
into a terrible river
with their hands chained,
stuffed into an iron cage.
And in that cage, underwater, struggling,
they are going through direct pain.
They are going through seeing
every nice thing collapse in their life.
While they're going through that
their body is also falling apart.
Let's imagine your mom.
Even your mom just in
this life is like that.
Her situation is super desperate.
To jump off the banks of the river,
to swim down underwater,
to open up their iron cage,
to get the chains off of her,
to pull her out of the
water, to get her to safety,
it's almost impossible.
Difficult. But at least
we should try to imagine
that it's something we would like to do.
So that gets you in the mind frame
of the third step
for developing bodhichitta,
Bodhisattva vision,
which is that you're,
if you want to pay your mom back
just get her out of the river.
Get her out of the cage.
Get her out of the handcuffs.
Paying your mom back for
everything she did for you
doesn't mean buy her new TV
when she's too old to work.
It's a little more complicated than that.
Let's go on to the next verse,
first verse of this section actually.
BSLAB BTUS LAS
BSLAB BTUS is called Shiksasamuccaya.
Shantideva,
Master Shantideva wrote two
great books that we have.
Of course the first one is
The Guide To The
Bodhisattva's Way Of Life.
And the other is a long description
of sutra quotations
that applied to training ourselves.
That's called Compendium of Trainings.
NYON MONGS KYIS SMYO
Your mom.
Imagine your mom.
SMYO means gone crazy,
like she went crazy.
Like I have a friend her mom,
this is in fact, this is a
big danger for older people
that they take their drugs wrong.
They forget they took their drugs already
and they take them three
or four times in a day,
or they take whole bottle by accident
and then they get crazy.
So imagine NYON MONGS KYIS SMYO
Your mom has gone crazy.
because of her mental afflictions,
her negative emotions.
GTI MUG LDONGS means her misunderstanding
of where life is coming
from has made her blind.
Her misunderstanding gouged out her eyes.
G-YANG SA MANG PO'I LAM DU NI
She's wandering in the high mountains
near all of these cliffs.
So she's blind and she's gone crazy,
and she's balancing on,
high in the Himalayas,
on these very dangerous cliffs.
GOM PA RE RE RDEG 'CHA' BA
Then you're watching her
take her unsteady steps
near the edge of these
deep abysses, deep chasms.
BDAG DANG GZHAN RTAG MYA NGAN GZHI
'GRO BA RNAMS NI SDUG BSNGAL MTSUNGS
So BDAG DANG GZHAN RTAG MYA NGAN GZHI
Our whole life is a misery.
'GRO BA RNAMS NI SDUG BSNGAL MTSUNGS
And the suffering
of living beings is similar
to a person who has gone mad,
and who is blinded, had
their eyes gouged out,
and is walking along these
high mountain canyons
where they could fall off easily.
ZHES GSUNGS PA LTAR, DPER NA,
TSE 'DI' AA MA MIG LONG ZHING
LONG KHRID DANG BRAL
Imagine your mom in this life, MIG LONG,
her eyes have been cut out.
LONG KHRID DANG BRAL means
imagine she has no one to guide her,
Aad she's just, like
thinking of your mom is blind
and she's walking through New York city
through the traffic.
And no one to help her
to get to the other side.
SEMS MYOS TE
On top of that she's
gone temporarily insane.
On top of being blind, she's insane
MYOS TE G-YANG SA ZHIG GI
KHAR MCHONG BAR NYE BA NA
and she's close to falling
off a very high cliff.
MCHONG means to jump.
But here it means to fall
off a very high cliff.
BU DE DER YOD NA
If her daughter or her son is nearby
at her side,
AA MA DES KYANG BU DE LA MI RE NA
if she can't hope,
if she can't put her hopes
in her child at her side,
then who else
is she going to put her hopes in?
If her child, her daughter or her son,
is walking next to her
through New York City traffic
while the mom is temporarily insane
and also blind, and if
that son or daughter
will not reach their hand out
and help them across the street,
then who can she hope?
Who else is she going to hope for?
BU DES KYANG AA MA DE MI
BSKYAB NA SU LA BSKYAB
If the child is going to protect someone
in their whole life,
if they're going to help someone
but they don't help their mom
when they are temporarily insane and blind
and about to die, because they're
going to fall off a cliff,
if the time has come to help her
and you don't help your own mom,
well then, who else you going to help?
How can you say you're a nice person?
How can you say you're
doing all this charity work
if you won't help your own
mom who's right next to you,
and who's going to die
in the next few minutes
if you don't grab her and help her?
Picture here we can see...
I was trying to find a picture somebody
running away from a fire.
It's not very good, right?
It looks like a thief or something.
But, I guess the website
that I used for pictures
they're all cheerful,
which is why I use it.
But anyway, imagine that this is your mom.
She's running from a fire in her home.
You are standing at the door.
You can just step in and take her hand
and bring her out.
And you don't.
Just imagine that you don't.
That's the feeling we're
supposed to get here.
DE BSHIN DU SEMS CAN
THAMS CAD KYAG CHOS DANG
CHOS MA YIN PA'I BLANG DOR
LTA BA'I MIG DANG NI BRAL
Every living being around us is blind.
People in the whole world
around us are blind,
especially if they don't
have any dharma training.
They don't know what's
the right thing to do
and what's the wrong thing to do.
Their judgment of what's
a good thing to do,
of what's a healthy thing to do
and what's a unhealthy thing to do,
their judgment about that
line is completely mistaken.
So even if they think about it
they're going to make the wrong decisions
about everything.
In that sense they are blind.
If you had a few minutes
or a few dollars extra,
if you studied Lam Rim,
then you would use it
to serve somebody else who needed help.
Or you would use the money
to help someone else who needed help.
But if you're blind, then you
would just buy a nice dinner
or something.
You would ignore those people.
That's blindness.
To not serve the poor,
to not serve people who are sick,
to not serve the environment,
it's a blindness. And
people are just blind.
And they're doing the
completely wrong thing.
So imagine your mom like that.
SKAD CIG RE RE ZHING 'DOD PA DANG
LAG LEN PHYIN CI LOG TU BYED PA
All of their hopes in life,
all of the goals they try to reach,
are completely mistaken.
LOG TU BYED PA'I NYES SPYOD
KYIS GOM PA RDEG 'CHA'
So every step they take in their life
is like a person dancing on a high cliff
and about to fall off.
Every step they take through life
with their eyes blinded is a dangerous,
is a dangerous step.
'DI BYED DANG 'DI MA BYED ZER BA'I
SLOB MKAHN BSHES GNYEN GYI
LONG KHRID DANG NI BRAL
They don't have anyone
who can take their arm
and guide them across the busy traffic,
or something like that.
Here it's called BSHES GNYEN, right?
DGE BA'I BSHES GNYEN - spiritual friend.
They don't have, most people in this world
don't have anybody who can grab their arm
and say, Come on,
help other people.
You want to be happy? Help other people.
That's the only way to be happy.
Take care of other people.
They don't have someone.
'DI BYED DANG 'DI MA BYED ZER
They don't have anybody who can tell them:
do this and don't do this.
This is a good thing to do.
That's a bad thing to do.
NYON MONGS DUG GSUM GYI
GDON GYIS SEMS DKRUNGS
NYON MONGS DUG GSUM
means the three animals at the
middle of the Wheel of Life:
misunderstanding your world,
and then ignorant liking,
and ignorant disliking.
Is it okay to like things? Yes.
Is it okay to like things
and try to take them away
from other people? No.
That's ignorant liking.
Is it okay to dislike things?
Yes, we should dislike cancer.
Is it okay to dislike
cancer in a way that you
take resources from other people?
I heard today...
Yes, some country was
blocking vaccinations
to another country
because they want it
all of them themselves.
And that's ignorant.
All right.
DUG GSUM GYI GDON
GDON means a demon.
GDON GYIS SEMS DKRUGS
DKRUGS means to...
Here's DKRUGS
I got this carrot juice
and if I wanted to...
This is called DKRUGS.
DKRUGS means to shake it up.
That's how you make a nice carrot juice
or something like that.
Let's see if it tastes good.
(people chuckle)
So that's called DKRUGS.
The people around us are
DKRUGS by the demon of
these three kinds of negative emotions.
SHES PA LA RANG DBANG MA THOB PAS SMYO
They cannot...
This is an interesting expression
SHES PA LA RANG DBANG
RANG DBANG means freedom or liberation.
Freedom in a political sense, for example.
They don't have RANG DBANG
about their own mind.
They don't have freedom
to think pure thoughts
because they're out of control.
SMYO means crazy.
What's the word for alcohol
in ancient scripture?
We call it SMYO BYED...SMYO BYED.
SMYO BYED means crazy
maker, makes you crazy.
SMYO NAS
BSKAL PA MANG POR ME DANG LUS DBYER MED DU
'GYUR BA'I NGAN SONG
They are about to fall off the cliff
into the deep canyon called
the three lower realms.
Where for many BSKAL PAs,
for many millions of years,
ME DANG LUS DBYER MED
your body and the fire
there are indistinguishable
one from the other.
You can't tell where your body starts
and where the fire starts.
NGAN SONG GI G-YANG SA CHEN POR
They're about to fall off that cliff.
'GRO BA 'DI LA
DA LAN RANG CAG DGE BA'I
BSHES GNYEN DANG MJAL
But us guys, RANG CAG
DGE BA'I BSHES GNYEN DANG MJAL
we have met with a spiritual teacher.
We had the great, good fortune
to meet awesome spiritual teachers.
THEG PA CHEN PO'I CHOS DANG PHRAD
We have made contact
with the Mahayana dharma.
With the dharma that says,
take care of other people.
Just to meet somebody who tells you
to take care of other
people is extremely rare.
To me, when you talk about
religions of the world:
Christianity, Islam,
Hinduism, Judaism,
they are all very rare, good luck.
Like don't focus on the
difference between them.
To meet any of them as a child,
or to grow up in a country
where any of them exist,
is extremely good karma.
Extremely good karma. Great karma.
THEG PA CHEN PO'I CHOS DANG PHRAD
BLANG DOR YANG CUNG ZAD SHES
We understand what we should
do, and what we shouldn't do,
CUNG ZAD - a tiny bit.
A tiny bit - CUNG ZAD.
We understand a tiny bit
about what we should do
or shouldn't do.
DE DAG LAS RANG CHES CHER BZANG BAS
In that sense
we are more blessed than our mom,
the blind crazy mom.
We have some eyes.
We have some sanity.
We are following Lam Rim.
That's a sign of sanity.
So I'm not the best person in the world,
but compared to someone
who never heard Lam Rim,
or never heard that you
should take care other people,
I'm like perfect.
Here is a funny word - CHES CHER BZANG.
I'm like super. I'm really perfect,
compared to these other people
who are blind and crazy.
At least I have eyes. I
don't use them very well.
And at least I'm not crazy.
Although it's crazy to act
crazy when you don't have to.
DE DAG DE LAS SKYOB THABS KYI KHUR BYED
The KHUR [burden] to take care
of my mom has fallen to me
because I am the only one
who has any eyes around here.
I'm the only one who
has Lam Rim around here.
BYED MKHAN RANG LA BABS TSUL
BABS TSUL means it has come down to me.
There's nobody else who can
take this responsibility.
It's all fallen - BABS - to me - BSAM PA.
So think about that.
I like this picture
of giving CPR to somebody,
trying to save somebody's live who's...
I don't know if you've had
this happen in your life.
If you live as long as
me and Jigme, it happens,
every 20 years or something
that you get to save somebody's life.
I remember somebody was on fire
and I was able to knock
them down and save them.
So in your...or in a car accident,
I pulled somebody out of a car.
It doesn't happen very often.
But it seems like a high honor
to have the chance to save a life.
Someone is going to die
if you don't do something
in the next two minutes.
And for some reason you don't freak out
and you think clearly for two minutes,
And you pull them out of the car
and the car blows up. And you are like,
"Damn, I did it."
And it happens a few times in your life.
It's one of the sweetest things in life
to be able to say I save somebody's life
is a great feeling.
It's one of the greatest feelings in life.
So anyway, you have a chance
right now to save your mom.
Your mom's had a car accident.
The car is about to blow up.
And all of us have this chance
to pull our mom out of the car.
YANG SLOB SPRING LAS
This is called A letter to a Student.
It was written by Master Chandragomi
about 1,300 or 1,400 years ago.
,NYE DU 'KHOR BA'I RGYA
MTSO'I KHONGS SU CHUD GYUR PA,
,KLONG GI NANG DU LHUNG
BA LTA BUR SNANG BZHIN DU,
,SKYE SHI 'PHOS PAS NGO
MA SHES PA DE BOR NAS,
,GAL TE GCIG THAR BYED
NA DE LAS KHREL BOR MED.
NYE DU means your loved
one, the people you love,
'KHOR BA'I RGYA MTSO
KHONGS SU CHUD GYUR PA
they have fallen into
the ocean of sansara,
suffering life.
KLONG GI NANG DU LHUNG
And there's a, what do you call that?
a whirlpool.
What do you call that? Because
there's another one for that.
Thers' a technical word for whirlpool
in the middle of the ocean.
It's like a vortex. Huh?
I don't know. You can check.
But anyway, your mom has
fallen into this whirlpool
in the middle of the ocean.
SNANG BZHIN DU, SKYE SHI 'PHOS PAS
She's moving from birth
to death, birth to death,
birth to death.
NGO MA SHES PA
Because she's been shifting
from birth to death,
and birth and death,
and because you've been
switching from birth to death
to birth to death, you
don't recognize her.
NGO MA SHES means you don't recognize
that she was your mom,
because there's been too
many deaths in between.
BOR NAS
And so you ignore her.
GAL TE GCIG THAR BYED NA
And you kind of say, I'm
going to focus on myself.
I think I'll just focus on myself.
I know these other people are suffering
but they are not... There's no big reason
why I should take care of them also.
You don't recognize that
they have been your mom.
DE LAS KHREL BOR MED
KHREL MED means you don't
care what others think.
Remember? When you do a bad deed
and you don't care
about what others think,
that's called KHREL MED
So here it means how could
you do anything more shameless
than to ignore your mom if
she's in the middle of drowning,
and you're just swimming off by yourself.
Did you find that thing?
[TL] I think that word
is maelstrom. [GMR] Yes.
I think maelstrom.
Yes. That sounds good.
CES PA LTAR MA SEMS CAN
'KHOR BA'I RGYA MTSO'I
KLONG DU CHUD PA RNAMS
DA RES RANG LA 'DON PA'I
THABS YOD BZHIN DU
Your mom fell into the
ocean. She's being suck down
by a maelstrom, whirlpool.
And you have... What
do you call those thing
you throw to the drowning
people? The ring.
- [Woman] Life saver.
- [GMR] Yes, you have the life ring?
- [GMR] Life saver?
Yes, and then you're just standing there
with the life saver and
you don't throw it to her?
What's wrong with you?
What kind of person are you?
Like you have a way called Lam Rim
and you could just throw to her,
and you're like, "Huh? What?
Oh, look she's drowning..."
THABS YOD BZHIN DU MA BTON NA
If you don't pull her out,
MA RABS
You should learn this word MA RABS.
MA RABS has nothing to do with mother.
And it has nothing to do with not really.
MA RABS means
worst of the worst.
It's a useful word.
MA RABS
MA RABS THA CHAD means you
are the worst of the worst
of all the people in the world.
You just really suck.
You stand there at the life preserver
and you watch your mom go
under. What's wrong with you?
That's MA RABS THA CHAD.
You are like the worst of the worst.
DE DAG 'DON PA'I KHUR DA RES
The KHUR, the responsibility or the burden
of pulling her out, which is 'DON.
DA RES RANG NYID LA BABS
BABS means the responsibility has fallen
on your shoulders.
So do it. 'DUG SNYAM DU DRIN GZO BSGOM
And that what it means to meditate
on repaying your mother's kindness.
So it's interesting. She gave you food.
She gave you language.
She gave you walking.
She gave you manners. She
gave you wearing clothes.
And when you say, you should pay her back
it feels like... Oh, you should feed her.
Or you should make sure she has clothes.
Or you should teach her Spanish
if she's speaking English or something.
And he says, no no no,
just save her life, okay, it's enough.
We're not talking about paying her back
with what she gave you,
we're talking about saving her life.
That's a difference. You can pay her back
not by buying her new dress
or by buying her a nice French dinner.
How about you just save her
life? That would be nice.
DRIN GZO BA DE YANG DBU MA SNYING PO LAS
Then he quotes a book called the
Essence of the Middle Way,
which is a famous book
by Master Bhavaviveka,
Lower Middle Way.
,GZHAN YANG SNGON CHAD NYON MONGS PA'I,
,GDON GYIS BRLAMS PA BDAG GIS NI,
SNGON CHAD means in the past.
NYON MONGS PA'I GDON GYIS BRLAMS PA
What do you call that when a
spirit takes over a person?
- [Tim] Possession.
- [GMR] Possession. Yes. I
was possessed by the demon.
I have been possessed by the demon
of my own negative emotions.
And because of that,
instead of trying to help my mom,
RMAS LA 'GYUR BYED
'GYUR BYED is an interesting word.
It means the changer, right Tim?
'GYUR BYED - the changer.
And it's a word for salt
because it changes the taste of a dish.
The changer.
RMAS misspelled here means open wound.
So I'm supposed to be the hero
who goes and saves my mom.
But what I've been
doing so far in my life,
because I was possessed by the
demon of my own selfishness,
I was rubbing salt in her wounds
instead of trying to
put a band-aid on them.
,SDUG BSNGAL NAD PA GANG SDUG BYAS,
I was doing my best to
make her condition worse.
I was pushing her off a cliff
after she went blind and crazy.
And I was like leading her to the
to the edge of the cliff.
,SKYE BA GZHAN DU GANG DAG GIS,
,BYAMS DANG BSNYEN BKUR PHAN PA BYAS,
Look, in other lives,
the people around you
have cared for you,
as literally as your mother.
They have BYAMS PA.
They have shown you BYAMS PA.
What's that, you guys?
Love. And BSNYEN BKUR
BSNYEN BKUR means they have respected you
and cared for you.
PHAN PA - They have given you
help your whole life long.
And in return,
LAN DU PHAN GDAGS PA
wouldn't you want to repay them in kind?
Wouldn't you want to give them
back the same kind of help?
What's the best one you can do?
MYA NGAN BZLA as a verb.
We had an in the Diamond Cutter Sutra.
MYA NGAN BZLA
Nirvanacize.
So here is a very strange verb.
It's almost an invented verb.
,MYA NGAN BLZA LAS GZHAN CI YOD,
There's no option.
Don't give them clothes back.
Don't give them food back. Give them back
nirvana and buddhahood. That's repayment.
That's DRIN GZO.
That's paying your mom back.
It's kind of common, right?
If someone gives you a gift
you're try to give them back
something better, right?
So, okay, you gave me
food. You gave me language.
You gave me walking. You
gave me dressing clothes.
You gave me human behavior.
I think I'll give you nirvana back
or buddhahood if you want.
That's a good deal.
All right.
That's the picture we have here
that we started out the class with.
Is this, you know,
the idea of the young girl,
she's paying her mom back.
She's giving her something beautiful.
The most beautiful things
you can give to your mom
to pay her back is nirvana and buddhahood.
CES PA LTAR ZAS DANG GOS
SOGS STER BA TZAM GYIS NI
Yeah you can give her food,
you can give her clothes.
GNAS SKABS KYI BKRES SKOM LAS GROL TZAM
She will reach a liberation
but only from hunger and thirst,
physical hunger, physical thirst.
LAS PHUGS SU PHAN PA ZHIG MI 'BYUNG
PHUGS SU means in the longterm.
She doesn't get... You can...
It's very common to buy your mom a TV
or an apartment even,
or something like that.
And he says, okay, that's
help, that's PHAN PA,
but not PHUGS SU.
That's not ultimately going
to help her that much.
BDE BA THAMS CAD DANG LDAN PA DANG
SDUG BSNGAL THAMS CAD
DANG BRAL BA ZHIG BYUNG NA
If she could get every form of happiness,
and if she could escape
every form of pain,
SEMS CAN DE DAG LA'ANG
PHAN PA BRTAN CING CHE LA
That's real payback.
That's a good pay back.
Give her every form of happiness
and remove every form of pain.
That's a good pay back.
DE YANG SANGS RGYAS KYI
GO 'PHANG LA BKOD NA
Now if you could push her to buddhahood,
if you could get her to go to buddhahood,
Yes, then BDE BA THAMS CAD,
she gets everything she ever wanted.
SDUG BSNGAL THAMS CAD DANG BRAL
She gets free of every
pain she ever wanted.
YIN PAS SEMS CAN THAMS CAD
SANGS RGYAS KYI GO 'PHANG LA
'GCOD PAR BYA'O SNYAM PA DGOS
Therefore, because
everyone has been your mom,
your motivation should
be to pay them back.
I'll push all of them into buddhahood.
I'll be the pusher. I will
get them into buddhahood.
DPER NA, RANG GI AA MA
SMYO NAS GRI KHYER TE
I love this image.
I went through this Lam Rim
three times with my teacher
over 30 years.
And I loved this image.
RANG GI AA MA
We use it a lot in DCI.
Suppose, I like to tell the story
because it happened kind of to me.
A friend of mine's mom,
who was living alone,
I was helping to take care of her
from time to time.
She had to take her meds every morning.
Later we had the hire someone
to give her her meds every morning
because she would take the wrong ones
or she would take the whole bottle.
She took a whole bottle of something.
And she went... What you
call it? Temporary insanity.
And she was cooking, and
she was cutting vegetables
with a big knife.
You can see the picture here.
It took me so long to find this picture.
I don't know why.
Yes, she was cutting vegetables
with this big meat cleaver.
And we told her...We went to the store.
We said we're coming back.
And we're coming back,
and we were trying to get the lock open
because she has sliding glass door
and it didn't work very well.
And she forgot that we were coming
And she thought it was a robber
or someone come to hurt her.
And she picked up the knife
And she heads towards the door.
And we were like, "Oh,
no, no, no! It's us!"
But when a ninety years
old woman is scared,
and she's got this cleaver in her hand,
and sometimes...
and this is the answer to a
question that you will get
as a Buddhist many, many
times from other people.
Okay, you're a Buddhist. Yes.
So what do you do if somebody attacks you?
If another country attacks you?
Or if a person attacks you with a knife?
Then what are you going to do?
What's the right thing to do?
The classic answer that you should learn
if you are going to teach Lam Rim
is treat them like your own mom.
If your own mom took some
extra drugs by accident
and went crazy, and then
you were coming in the door,
and she thought you were
someone come to hurt her
and she came to you with a big knife,
then would you shoot her?
Would you stab her?
And then no, of course I wouldn't.
Well what would you do?
Well, I will try to
wrestle her to the ground
and try to get the knife out of her hands.
Well what if she cut you?
Well, that's okay. It's worth it.
She gave me a few cuts.
It's better than killing her.
I wouldn't take a gun
and shoot my own mom.
I would take a few cuts.
So that's the answer to the question of
what to do if someone attacks you?
Try to -- What do you call that? --
disabled them or disarm them.
Even if it causes you
some pain or some trouble,
even serious trouble, it's
better than killing them
because they are your mom.
They have been your mom.
You wouldn't shoot you mom
if she came at you with a knife,
even in America. I don't think so.
So anyway, here is the Tibetan
RANG GI AA MA SMYO NAS
Suppose your mom went crazy,
GRI KHYER TE
and suppose she approached
you with a knife,
BU RANG NYID GSOD PAR RTZOM
RTZOM here means to undertake or to start.
It can also means to write a book.
So you have to be careful.
RTZOM NA'ANG AA MA LA MI KHRO BAR
You would not get angry at your mom.
You wouldn't get furious and say,
"Mom, I'm going to kill you."
MI PHRO BAR SMYO NAD DE SEL THABS
You would try to knock her down
and you would try to keep her safe
until the craziness passed from her mind.
BRTZON DGOS PA
You have to work hard to do it that way.
BZHIN DU DGRA LA'ANG DRIN GZO BYA DGOS
Then Pabongka Rinpoche ends this section
by saying,
I'm talking about people
who've been your mother
who are your enemy in this life.
I'm talking about people
who hurt you in this life:
people in your business,
other business executives
who trying to screw you,
or other country's people
who are attack your country
and try to kill you or hurt you,
people in your family who are jealous
or do things to hurt you.
I'm saying they have been
your mom and DRIN GZO.
It's time to payback.
There's a James Brown
song The Big Payback.
It's time for payback.
But payback in Buddhism means
it's time to push them into
nirvana and buddhahood,
not to pay them back by
hurting them more than they hurt you.
All right. Great words.
Difficult to practice.
And we'll see you in the next
Lam Rim episode. Thank you.